Alejandro Rodrigo

Cognitive and Behavioral Research

Vancouver, BC V5W 1Z3 alejandrodrigo86@gmail.com +1 204 370 9006

Professional with more than 10 years of experience in basic and applied research. Ph.D. Candidate and Master's in Behavioral Sciences: Experimental Analysis of Behavior. My research focuses on studying the cognitive mechanisms involved in spatial navigation and orientation in vertebrates. Founding Partner and Chief Operating and Commercial Officer of the company Walden Modular Equipment. The company's objective is to develop personalized experimental laboratory equipment used mainly in areas related to the study of behavior.

Personal Details

Highest Level of Education: Doctoral Degree

Total years of experience: 9

Work Experience

Chief Operating Officer

Walden Modular Equipment - Guadalajara, Jal.

September 2018 to Present

- Overseeing day-to-day administrative and operational functions of the company.
- Coordination of the development, production, marketing, and finance departments' actions.
- Ensure the company complies with the local laws and regulations.
- Manage and expand the client portfolio.
- Supervision and improvement of customer service and satisfaction guidelines.
- Control of future investments and purchases.

Coordinator of the Animal Welfare Department

Africam Safari - Puebla, Pue.

June 2011 to January 2013

- Coordination of undergraduate students and volunteers involved in the environmental enrichment program.
- Scheduling day-to-day activities of the program.
- Overseeing electronic documentation and reports on environmental enrichment and animal training programs.
- Review of safety protocols based on institutional guidelines to provide and improve the well-being of animals.
- Provision of expertise about the biology of species to media and zoo guests.

Education

Doctoral Degree in Experimental Analysis of Behavior

University of Guadalajara, Center of Studies and Research in Behavioral Sciences - Guadalajara, Jal. July 2017 to Present

Master's Degree in Experimental Analysis of Behavior

University of Guadalajara, Center of Studies and Research in Behavioral Sciences - Guadalajara, Jal. January 2014 to July 2017

Bachelor's Degree in Veterinary Medicine

Autonomous Metropolitan University - Ciudad de México April 2005 to September 2009

Skills

- Microsoft Office (10+ years)
- Writing skills (6 years)
- Strategic Planning (4 years)
- Research (10+ years)
- Laboratory Experience (8 years)
- Statistical software (R and R Studio) (5 years)
- Data Visualization (8 years)
- Data Collection (10+ years)
- Analytics (8 years)

Languages

- English Advanced
- Spanish Advanced

Links

https://alejandrodrigo86.github.io/Web/

https://waldenme.com/index.html

Awards

Jacksonville Zoo & Gardens New World Conservation Training Award

November 2011

Full funded scholarship awarded to attend the professional training program course: "Principles of Program Animal Management" of the Association of Zoos and Aquariums (AZA)

Kuczaj Memorial Travel Grant

October 2018

Grant to cover the conference fees at the XIX Biennial Meeting of the International Society for Comparative Psychology.

Humane Society International (HSI) Student Travel Awards

lune 2021

Award to cover the registration costs to attend the International Society for Applied Ethology 2021 congress.

Publications

Does stress run through the leash? An examination of stress transmission between owners and dogs during a walk

https://doi.org/10.1007/s10071-020-01460-6

January 2021

Contribution Role:

- Software: Programming and implementing R code to tide, order,
- manipulate, and analyze data.
- Formal Analysis: Application of linear regression and Generalized Linear Mixed Models (GLMM) analysis.
- Investigation: Assist in the data collection process.
- Writing original draft: Preparation of the published work, specifically writing the subsection Data analysis and the Results section of the initial draft.
- Visualization: Programming and implementing R code to visualize and present data.

Drug use as a coping style to social isolation by COVID-19 pandemic and its effects on the adherence to safety guidelines in Mexico

https://doi.org/10.28931/riiad.2021.1.04/331

March 2021

Contribution Role:

- Conceptualization: Assessment formulation to evaluate the effects of lockdown over drug use.
- Methodology: Design of the model using a cross-sectional design and a snowball sampling strategy.
- Software: Plan, design, and creation of online assessment using Google Forms.
- Investigation: In charge of collecting data using social media marketing to recruit participants across Mexico (n = 475). Writing Original Draft: Translation of the manuscript from Spanish to English.

Daily Patterns of Foraging and Aggressive Behaviors in Great-tailed Grackle (Quiscalus mexicanus) at an Urban Patch with Availability or Absence of Resources

https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.14.448443

June 2021

Contribution Role:

• Conceptualization: Formulated the research question regarding how Grackles allocate their behaviors around an urban food patch across 25 days to determine if the presence or absence of garbage collection changes the feeding strategy of the birds.

- Methodology: Design of a continuous sampling method (n = 194 hours of video).
- Software: Undergraduate training to code behavioral data using Open-Source Software (OSS) BORIS. Data analysis using R and R Studio.
- Formal Analysis: Application of GLMM analysis. Investigation: In charge of data collection. Resources: Provision of instrumentation to conduct field recordings.
- Writing original draft: Preparation and creation of the preprint manuscript.
- Visualization: Programming and implementation of the R code to visualize and present data. Supervision: Oversight and leadership responsibility for the research activity planning and execution.
- Project administration: Management and coordination responsibility for the research activity planning and execution.